<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title>merlin&#x27;s blog</title>
	<link href="https://merlinshabaj.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="https://merlinshabaj.github.io"/>
	<generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
	<updated>2022-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	<id>https://merlinshabaj.github.io/atom.xml</id>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Discipline Equals Freedom, Jocko Willink</title>
		<published>2022-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://merlinshabaj.github.io/books/discipline-equals-freedom/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://merlinshabaj.github.io/books/discipline-equals-freedom/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;book-thoughts&quot;&gt;Book Thoughts&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;discipline-equals-freedom-jocko-willink&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Discipline Equals Freedom,&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; Jocko Willink&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am going to refer solely to the first part of the book, since this is the part about philosophy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;thoughts&quot;&gt;Thoughts&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking you can say that his philosophy is close to my personal philosophy of &lt;em&gt;Will&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and that there are many overlapping points. 
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
By reading this book I got a better understanding of my own philosphy regarding &lt;em&gt;Will&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and could refine some concepts. &lt;br&gt;
In one instance he made me understand that knowledge must be a part of exercising in &lt;em&gt;Will&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Interesting concepts:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The count is zero
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;each day you start at zero, which leaves you less room for excuses and weakness&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;being aggressive &#x2F; proactive
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not meant in a &lt;em&gt;people&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;-attacking way but in a &lt;em&gt;weakness&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;-attacking way&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;attacking your weakness relentlessly and always striving &#x2F; seeking out to tackle your weaknesses&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“The truth is what makes discipline unavoidable.”&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&quot;recommendation&quot;&gt;Recommendation&lt;&#x2F;h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although this book is almost written in a way where the focus lies on motivating the reader, I think the first part is a good read to gain a &lt;strong&gt;partial&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; overview of my own principle of &lt;em&gt;Will&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
The second part isn&#x27;t a good read.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Everything is fucked, Mark Manson</title>
		<published>2022-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://merlinshabaj.github.io/books/everything-is-fucked/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://merlinshabaj.github.io/books/everything-is-fucked/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;book-thoughts&quot;&gt;Book Thoughts&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;everything-is-fucked-mark-manson&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Everything is fucked,&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; Mark Manson&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;bullet-points&quot;&gt;Bullet Points&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;god value is your the value that sits at the top of your value hierachy &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;spiritual religions, ideological religions, interpersonal religions&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the &lt;em&gt;Human Formula&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; no hope is needed
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Act that you use humanity, whether in your own person, or in the person of any other, always at the same time as an end, never merely as a means.”&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;moral development explained by stage child, adolescent, adult (at some point this development is unrelated to age)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;childish: narcissistic, pleasure guided (e.g. left- or right-wing extremists = childish)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;adolescent: transactional (e.g. Joscha)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;adult: virtue oriented&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“-isms” are (ideological) religions (e.g. feminism, communism, etc.)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hope is destructive, at least it can be&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pain is a constant in human life &#x2F; humans don&#x27;t exist without pain
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;only question is whether you engage in it or avoid it &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;the quality of our lives is determined by the quality of our character, and the quality of our character is determined by our relationship with pain.”&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pursuit of happiness is an avoidance of growth, maturity and virtue
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is childish, it treats us and ourselves as means to some emotional end&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you will never be able to reach pure happiness in your life. 10 out of 10 happiness isn’t attainable&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stoics didn’t pursuit happiness, but character, the ability to sustain pain and make appropriate sacrifices&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;virtues are forms of practicing antifragility, these principles gain from chaos and adversity, hence the name antifragile
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;adult values are antifragile&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;childish values are fragile&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;adolescent values are also fragile like childish ones, just a little more robust&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pain is valueable and linked to growth&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“When we pursue pain, we are able to &lt;em&gt;choose&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; what pain we bring into our lives. And this choice makes the pain meaningful—and therefore, it is what makes life feel meaningful.&amp;quot; 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pain is the source of all value in life&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“To numb ourselves to our pain is to numb ourselves of anything that matters in the world.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;meditation is a way of dealing with pain
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bringing thinking and feeling brain together &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Blue Dot Effect&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;there is a happiness baseline &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sometimes you are above or below but after some time you always find yourself back on the baseline &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;even when your life drastically changes forever
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;human decide with their feelings, hence the name feelings economy&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;diversion and innovation are two ways of creating value in the market 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;innovation: upgrading a pain (e.g. new medicine, heart surgery, internet)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;diversion: means of avoiding pain (e.g. movie theaters, weekend trips, cocaine)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“give the people what they want” works with innovations and is destructive when you give them (too many) diversions&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“If the pursuit of happiness pulls us all back into childishness, then fake freedom conspires to keep us there.”
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;variety doesn’t equal freedom&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;only real form of freedom, is throuegh self-limitation
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pleasure, diversions, variety all never last&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pain of physical exercise =&amp;gt; healthier, stronger body&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sacrifice of a strong work ethic =&amp;gt; more job opportunities, more money, control over one&#x27;s career&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;willingness to engage in conflict =&amp;gt; free you to talk to anyone, align with people, support each other&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;most meaningful freedom comes from commitments
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some things are only attainable by depth, which greater commitment allows for
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;having lived in one place for 50 years (familiarity and intimacy with people and culture)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;having played the guitar for 20 years (artistic expression)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fake freedom (ff) demands more, while real freedom (rf) is the conscious decision to live with less
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;ff&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is addictive (can always have more variety &#x2F; options), has diminishing return (need more for the same high), sees the world as a transaction, requires the world to conform to your will&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;ff&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; consists mostly of options and variety (means-to-an-end mentality)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;rf&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is repetitive and predictable, has increasing returns, sees the world unconditionally, with the only victory being over your own desire, requires nothing besides your own will&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;North Korea isn’t free because they can’t choose what music to listen to or which TV channel to watch, but because they can’t choose their sacrifices&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;democracy requires citizens of strong maturity and character (you need internal and external sacrifices for democracy)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plato identified cycles as well, freedom to tyranny (similarly to Stefan Aarnio in &lt;em&gt;Hard Times Create Strong Men&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;inevitable for democracy to lead to moral decay as they start to indulge in &lt;em&gt;ff&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Thusly people adopt more childish values, they don’t want to endure pain for the sake of greater freedom, which ends up with people wishing for a strong leader who fixes all the problems—a tyrant.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Can&#x27;t Hurt Me, David Goggins</title>
		<published>2022-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://merlinshabaj.github.io/books/cant-hurt-me/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://merlinshabaj.github.io/books/cant-hurt-me/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;book-thoughts&quot;&gt;Book Thoughts&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;can-t-hurt-me-david-goggins&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Can’t Hurt Me,&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; David Goggins&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;bullet-points&quot;&gt;Bullet points&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;awakening was mental&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;all my problems I ever had were mental
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Will&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is what you use when waging war against yourself&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Will&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is mental&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my core is or was: shy, sensitive, timid&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;thoughts&quot;&gt;Thoughts&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout my whole life, ever since my awakening, I have been on the lookout to train my &lt;em&gt;Will&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. I knew that &lt;em&gt;Will&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is a thing that I need in order to grow. With &lt;em&gt;Will&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; I would be able to take complete ownership of my core. &lt;br&gt;
That is the reason why, after my awakening, I started to engage in waking up early, running, training, stretching and cold showers.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
David Goggins dedicated his life to &lt;em&gt;Will&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. His core is different from mine, although there is overlap. 
I understand David—despite me not knowing him personally he feels pretty familiar to me. &lt;br&gt;
There is no glory in pursuing &lt;em&gt;Will&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, no one will come and pat you on your back or will be there to admire what you’ve done. Ultimately no one can understand the pain you went through or are going through.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Seeking out pain, embracing it, engaging in it, develops your character in all facets of life. Pain is strongly related to purpose.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Peace is linked to all of that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>The subtle art of not giving a fuck, Mark Manson</title>
		<published>2022-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://merlinshabaj.github.io/books/subtle-art/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://merlinshabaj.github.io/books/subtle-art/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;book-summary&quot;&gt;Book Summary&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-subtle-art-of-not-giving-a-fuck-mark-manson&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Subtle Art of Not giving a Fuck,&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; Mark Manson&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;most-important-thoughts&quot;&gt;Most important thoughts:&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the values you set for yourself determine which fucks you give — what you care about&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;emotions shouldn’t be surpressed they offer you deeper insight into your mind
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;values&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;subconscious &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;deficiencies&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;suffering is the source of most profound happiness 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can’t avoid suffering and death&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;backwards law&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you are not special 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;being colloquially speaking average isn’t bad (weird concept—makes sense to some degree)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-of-his-values&quot;&gt;Some of His Values:&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;take 100% responsibility for your life
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;responsibility does not equal fault&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;takes away the room for excuses, blame, entitlement&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;puts you in a position of full leadership over your own life&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;look death into the eye
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;death is a part of life &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;similar to stoic philosophy&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;question yourself — you are wrong
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;what if I am wrong?”, “What would be the consequence of me being wrong?”, “Would me being wrong create a better or worse problem than my current problem, for both myself and others?&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;being honest
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;american vs. russian culture of honesty&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rejecting alternatives in terms of commitment 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rejection of alternatives liberates&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reject what doesn’t align with most important values &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rejection of constant pursuit of breadth without depth&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;though breadth has it’s place as well but depth is where the gold is buried&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“do something” principle
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;similar to jordan peterson cleaning up your room &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if you lack energy or direction start by doing something, doesn’t matter what it is, you will accumalate energy and move forward&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;motivation shouldn’t be looked at like this: &lt;br&gt;
Inspiration -&amp;gt; Motivation -&amp;gt; Action but rather like this: &lt;br&gt;
Action -&amp;gt; Inspiration -&amp;gt; Motivation it is about the reaction of the action that makes you move forward and ellicits the felling of motivation&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Man&#x27;s search for meaning, Viktor Frankl</title>
		<published>2022-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://merlinshabaj.github.io/books/search-for-meaning/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://merlinshabaj.github.io/books/search-for-meaning/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;book-summary&quot;&gt;Book Summary&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;man-s-search-for-meaning-viktor-frankl&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Man’s search for meaning,&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; Viktor Frankl&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;most-important-thoughts&quot;&gt;Most important thoughts:&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;suffering is an ineradicable part of life, like death&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the only freedom you will always have is the freedom to choose in which way to react to things 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Man is self-determined, choosing which one to become (saint or swine) is at your own volition&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the meaning of your life will be completely revealed to you at the end of our life. Similiar to a movie, which is made up of thousands upon thousands of pictures, you do not understand the context of a given picture without the pictures before; the same goes for the end of a movie.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you can find meaning in these three areas:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;achievement -&amp;gt; publishing a book,&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;love&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;suffering.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;meaning is individual&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“the salvation of man is through love and in love”&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“I wish to stress that the true meaning of life is to be discovered in the world rather within man or his own psyche, as though it were a closed system.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;experience-in-concentration-camp&quot;&gt;Experience in Concentration Camp:&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you get stripped of everything
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your achievements&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your possessions &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your dignity&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your name gets replaced with a number&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your clothes&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;all of your hair&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;-&amp;gt; you end up being just a body of meat, many things that you could have built your ego upon were rendered worthless in an instant.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you are around death all the time&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;close to starvation&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hard physical labour&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;random attacks by guards&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bad and broken clothing including shoes -&amp;gt; dealing with the cold&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sleeping with 9 men in one bed in a non-heated room and only having two blankets&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lice &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;swollen limbs (legs in particular) because of cold &amp;amp; labour&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;death of people around you was a “casual sight”&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;developed apathy&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;constantly living on the edge of survival&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;reactions-of-prisoners&quot;&gt;Reactions of prisoners:&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saints, minority of people behaved like saints despite the conditions and looked out for other people, helped other people etc.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Swine, a lot of people’s behaviour could be described as deceitful, self-serving at the cost of others etc. Some were worse than SS guards (especially because some became a Capo).&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;prisoners who lost hope usually underwent the same “procedure” -&amp;gt; first started to embrace carelessness and apathy, laying in their own feces, urine and losing any interest to move even despite motivating guards. Finally, they 
most of the time smoked a cigarette which almost clearly signaled to everyone that he is going to die in next 48 hours. &lt;br&gt;
-&amp;gt; clearly shows the magnitude of meaning.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Viktor mentioned how he helped other prisoners beat their hopelessness by finding meaning in their lives.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For new arrivals all of the common sights in the camp are disgusting and deeply troubling, but over time he gets desensitized and it becomes normality. E.g. stealing shoelaces &#x2F; shoes from a person that has just died became normality.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;interesting-occurences-in-the-camp&quot;&gt;Interesting occurences in the camp:&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spiritual speeches were held&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prisoners had no sexual lust, other more important needs weren’t satisfied&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vikor’s love to his wife, he felt a spiritual connection to her &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-thoughts&quot;&gt;My thoughts:&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everything that can be stripped away from you like they did with new arrivals in Auschwitz is not qualified to be a source of self-esteem.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Concentration camps show the real&#x2F;pure strength in people. When you can’t inflate your “strength&amp;quot; with physicality, reputation, money etc. you can see your true strength. &lt;br&gt;
-&amp;gt; true strength is important, these outer qualities aren’t pure.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
This means when judging yourself you should strip yourself of any of these tainted qualities, to see your real form. (recall Meditations)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;extended-summary&quot;&gt;Extended summary:&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this summary I am going to start with significant experiences he had in the concentration camps, then go on and explain how prisoners reacted and conclude with his most important thoughts.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experiences in the concentration camps&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon arrival all new prisoners get stripped of everything they possess, except for some clothes. Additionally they shave off all the hair of everyone and replace their names with numbers. Thusly this means that often a lot and sometimes everything they used to build up their egos e.g. reputation, financial success or diplomas held no worth anymore, in an instant. At this point they were mere human bodies &#x2F; flesh. 
Afterwards a normal day in the camp looked like the following: first they are woken up by a shrill whistle and have to gather outside of their huts, where they then began the march to their workplace. They underwent hard physical labour in the cold with insufficient clothes and tools. The daily food they got was a little piece of bread and little bit of watery soup once a day. In addition to that, every minor misbehaviour got punished severely by the guards and sometimes they beat up prisoners for no reason. Furthermore, they shared one bed and two blankets with nine men in a non-heated room and suffered from lice. 
The sight of dead people and prisoners getting beaten up was a normal one in the camp, which desensitized the prisoners. Besides that they also had to deal with diseases, inflammations and swollen limbs because of the cold and hard labour. Generally, it was not a good to be spotted as handicapped by the guards which could render you useless and ultimately lead to death. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reactions of prisoners&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frankl observed two kinds of prisoner, the first one being a saint and the second one being a swine. 
On the one hand the people he used to describe as saints were people who, despite their hardship, still tried to be good, helped other people etc. On the other hand, swine were people whose behaviour was deceitful, self-serving at the cost of others etc. Some of these people were worse than SS guards, especially if they became a Capo (a prisoner who was assigned to supervise labour and other tasks). Some of the Capos abused the prisoners even more than the SS itself.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than that he observed a pattern in prisoners who lost hope and saw no purpose in their suffering anymore. 
Beginning with increasing carelessness and apathy these prisoners stopped moving usually they would stay in bed, not eat and would not even stand up to go to the toilet. As soon as these people smoked a cigarette the prisoners around would know that they would die within the next 48 hours.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Viktor also mentioned cases in which he helped such people overcome this kind of hopelessness by discovering a meaning for their life, which had drastic effects on their mental health. 
(“He who has a why to live can bear almost any how.” Friedrich Nietzsche)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions and Thoughts&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Viktor Frankl comes to the conclusion that the only freedom you have is the freedom to choose how to react to things. Ultimately Man is self-determined, choosing to become a saint or swine in the context of the concentration camp is at your own volition. 
He also concludes that meaning is individual and unique to each person specifically. Moreover he says that the meaning of life always changes but never ceases to exist. Meaning can be found in three areas: achievement, love and suffering.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meaning through achievement can be found by creating a work or doing a deed.&lt;br&gt;
Meaning through love can be found by encountering someone or experiencing something.&lt;br&gt;
Meaning through suffering can be found by the attitude we take toward these unavoidable situations.&lt;br&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;unfinished&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Fighting</title>
		<published>2022-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://merlinshabaj.github.io/notes/fighting/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://merlinshabaj.github.io/notes/fighting/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;fighting&quot;&gt;Fighting&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-do-i-have-the-desire-to-fight-stepping-into-the-cage&quot;&gt;Why do I have the desire to fight, stepping into the cage?&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a long time I have been interested in everything regarding fighting. Even when my story began and I started to go for runs in the morning, at some point I trained my kicking ability and watched a lot of videos about learning martial arts. &lt;br&gt;
Until now I have always had the thoughts of competing officially in martial arts. I wrestled and did boxing with Leon, Hadi and even with Marlon (primarily boxing). Currently and for the pasts months I am consuming a lot of UFC content, I am interested in fighters stories and the adversity they overcome. In addition to that people like David Goggins possess the same “warrior” traits, I am intrigued by. The book “Relentless” inspires &#x2F; awakens the same in me. So far running has served to this desire or was a substitution for fighting, because it invokes the same feeling in me. Running is also a hard fight with myself, a battle in my mind, a constant doubt whether to quit or to keep running &#x2F; fighting and enduring the pain and hardship.
This is something that makes me &lt;strong&gt;feel alive&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; like no other thing in my life. Everytime I go for a run it is a test of mental strength and fortitude. But I think it isn’t as hard as fighting and does not challenge me in the same way as fighting would. Fighting is the ultimate display of mental fortitude, it involves a lot more pain, it is faster paced meaning you always have to keep your mental fortitude up and can never let down even for a second -&amp;gt; extremely high form of mindfulness.
If won a fight, you go home with a victory unlike running where you can always do more, even when you score a new personal best being extremely exhausted, I think it doesn’t translate the same like a bloody fight, a war. Fighting goes deeper, it hits your human core and thusly conveys a feeling even the most beautiful tragedy couldn’t convey. It makes me cry, become emotional but also makes me strong, and unstoppable at the same time. Fighting builds up emotion and releases emotion in fluent, natural way -&amp;gt; this makes you feel alive. It is a huge source of strength. I can’t get the same from running.&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
The desire to step in the cage and express and let out exactly these emotions.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;code&gt;CONTENT BELOW WAS DELETED ONCE. THIS IS JUST AN APPROXIMATION OF IT:&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;br&gt;
I know that I have a talent for this, throwing myself into the fire and coming out stronger. And not only that it also strengthens and fosters this natural ability &#x2F; talent of mine. And in my everyday life this constant desire to do that isn’t satisfied. Even though I am already doing things that nobody else is doing and with that means that I am alone on my path and have to create the path in the first place which also needs a fair portion of mental fortitude. Nontheless it can not be compared to fighting - so far running is the activity that comes the closest to it.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;code&gt;END OF DELETED CONTENT&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The story of being this fighter, this Rocky type of guy, being in extreme adversity and overcoming it, is a wonderful story, which I to some degree already live but which I would also like to foster even more and fighting is the thing that can accomplish that in the right way. I love to indulge in exactly that, it is beautiful.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;update-4th-of-december&quot;&gt;Update 4th of December&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week I went for a 34km run, the longest distance I’ve ever run so far and a 13km jump from the second longest distance I’ve ever run. This run was extremely challenging and I would say I exactly tapped into the my core with all of the emotions described above. &lt;br&gt;
This means it is possible to tap into that with just running. &lt;br&gt;
Furthermore I disagree with what I said regarding, that running is open ended and fighting isn’t, both are open ended. I don’t think I could ever feel complete after a fight, for longer than just a moment. Same goes for running.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
I completly forgot about that and in a recent note I talked about exactly these emotions, just to find them already written down here. Even though I didn&#x27;t have the experience back then, I perfectly anticipated how this would play out.&lt;br&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
